<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The eighth part of The Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator wherein certain doctrines ... are examined, and in order to a decision of the controversie ... an adress [sic] is made to a book entituled, An Adress to Protestants, given forth by W.P. anno 1679 ... / by W.R.</title>
            <title>Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 8</title>
            <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36272821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36272821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2237:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The eighth part of The Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator wherein certain doctrines ... are examined, and in order to a decision of the controversie ... an adress [sic] is made to a book entituled, An Adress to Protestants, given forth by W.P. anno 1679 ... / by W.R.</title>
                  <title>Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 8</title>
                  <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: William Rogers.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Address to Protestants upon the present conjuncture.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150237:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EIGHTH PART OF THE Chriſtian-Quaker, Diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Apoſtate &amp; Innovator,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">WHEREIN Certain DOCTRINES (Vindicated in Print, by ſuch as are repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Party with <hi>G. Fox</hi>) are Examined, and in order to a Deciſion of the Controverſie (which ſeemes to depend on the Truth or Falſhood thereof) an Adreſs is made to a Book Entituled, <hi>An Adreſs to Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants;</hi> Given forth by <hi>W. P. Anno</hi> 1679. and may now be termed, a Proper <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpirage</hi> in the caſe.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>W. R.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>BEfore I proceed to ſay any thing in purſuance of the Title Page, I think it meet to give a brief account of the chief matters aimed at, or treated on in the firſt ſeven Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker;</hi> not knowing, but that this ſmall Tract may be extended amongſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> farther than the reſt, and ſo may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſuch as are deſirous more fully to know what<note n="*" place="margin">The Reader may Note, that when I uſe the Words <hi>us,</hi> or <hi>we,</hi> 'tis with reſpect to ſuch (beſides my ſelf) as encouraged the Publication of other Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker.</hi>
               </note> we ſtand for, and againſt, to enquire after other Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> a part of thoſe things touching which we were once at Unity, the ways and means whereby that Unity was broken, are manifeſted.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150237:2"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Second Part,</hi> Doctrines of Truth (cleared from <hi>Objections</hi>) are laid down, that ſo it may be known more perfectly, than by the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> what the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> ſtandeth for.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third Part,</hi> Government is more largely diſcourſed on, than in the two foregoing Parts. Shewing, That the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi> owns but two ſorts. The one is the <hi>Outward Government</hi> under which we live, unto the Laws whereof we owe either Active or Paſſive Obedience, and ought not by outward Force to endeavour deliverance from under ſuch Laws, as we have, or may tern Oppreſſive.</p>
            <p>The other is, The <hi>Inward Government</hi> of Chriſt (who alone is Lord over the Conſcience) which is not repreſented by perſons viſible by carnal Eyes, inveſted with Power from him to execute Outward Laws, Edicts or Decrees, in an Outward Form of Government, viſible as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Fifth Parts,</hi> 'Tis manifeſted, That <hi>G. F.</hi> hath Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneouſly concerned himſelf in the <hi>Diviſions</hi> amongſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and is therein become a Reproach and Scandale to the Truth, which the <hi>Children of Light</hi> profeſs and walk in.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Sixth Part,</hi> is manifeſted, The wickedneſs of Two ſmall Tracts written on the occaſion of the Publication of the firſt <hi>Five Parts</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker.</hi> One by <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor,</hi> Wherein he hath abuſed me at a ſordid rate, as by his Book appears, and yet hath not quoted one Word out of my Writings to prove any Recriminating Reflection on me, more than the beginning of my Title Page, <hi>viz. The Chriſtian-Quaker diſtinguiſhed from the Apostate and Innovator.</hi> Had not the ſaid <hi>Christopher Taylor</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelf (as he is a Publick Preacher) a <hi>Church-Governour,</hi> and that 'tis the Duty of ſome others to pin their Faith on his Sleeve, How could he have attempted ſo unconvincing a Work? Had he no Credit on a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcore to looſe, me-thinks he ſhould never have hazarded his Reputation as a Man (if ever he had any) to write at ſo Envious a rate as he hath, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Reader, That the very Title of my Book was Blaſphemous. 'Tis hard to Imagine wherein the concludes the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> to be, unleſs in theſe Words, <hi>George Fox Detected;</hi> which then muſt imply, That, in his ſence, <hi>G. F. is, at leaſt, the Christ of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other ſmall Tract taken notice of, is given forth in the Name of <hi>John Pennington,</hi> worthy of no better Character than that of <hi>C. Taylor;</hi> the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therein aimed at, is to ſhew, That I abuſed his Father, and performed not my word in not citing all his Fathers Teſtimony: whereas If I had quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his Fathers Teſtimony, I had been worſe than my word. But that which adds to his Sin, is this, he hath charged me with making Inferences or Deductions that were untrue, when as I made no Inference nor Deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all from his Fathers words, as is manifeſted more fully in the ſaid 6th.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150237:2"/>
               <hi>Part.</hi> I do not doubt but that the aforeſaid Treatiſes were approved by the <hi>Second-days Meeting,</hi> elſe why have they in their Book Entituled<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>12th.</hi> Page of the Introduction.</note> 
               <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. Signified that the Names of ſome are already concern'd in Print, meaning in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker in Five Parts.</hi> What man of Reaſon, Conſcience, and Religion can conclude other than on this wiſe: <hi>That the pretended Government</hi> (under which ſuch irreligious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian-like treatment is approved) is a meer cheat, giving a kind of ſafe conduct (ſo far as is in their Power) to the Inſtruments of Satan, when frait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Antichriſtian-Arrows</hi> to wound the <hi>Children of Light,</hi> and <hi>Lambs of God.</hi> But notwithſtanding this evil Treatment, the ſaid 6th. <hi>Part</hi> contains <hi>Chriſtian Propoſitions</hi> for a Reconciliation. Therein is alſo ſomething ſaid to diſcover the emptineſs and weakneſs of <hi>Thomas Laurence</hi> his three quarters of a Sheet, who telling the Reader that he is 81 years of age, Charity oblie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges me not to be ſevere upon him.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Seventh Part</hi> are detected a part of the Forgeries, Prevarications, and Errours wherewith a Treatiſe Entituled, <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. given forth in the Name of the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker in Five Parts,</hi> is ſtuft, and is an additional Evidence againſt the ſaid Meeting that they themſelves are eſpouſing the Cauſe of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovation,</hi> and by the ſcope of ſome Parts of their Treatiſe of nameleſs Authors (referred to <hi>Richard Richardſons</hi> ſmall Tract ſtiled, <hi>A few Ingredients,</hi> &amp;c. ſufficiently Papiſtical) have ſhown themſelves more nearly related to <hi>Popiſh</hi> Principles and Practiſes, than to the Principle and Practiſe of the <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſmall Tract is now written for the ſakes of ſuch among the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as are not yet principled to pin their Faiths on anothers Sleeve, but rather to hear, to ſee, and underſtand for themſelves in matters relating to the Kingdom of God, and Salvation of Souls. In confidence that 'twill find acceptance with ſuch; tis now publiſh't chiefly to evidence what from the Title may be expected.</p>
            <p>Of late days this Doctrine hath been publiſhed by ſuch as are reputed of <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Party. That in ſome Caſes that Conſciences of Believers ought to be bound by the poſitive Sentence of others, (meaning other Believers pretending to Authority as a Church, and not by election of Perſons) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaving any liberty for a Believer to refuſe on the account of not ſeeing it his Duty to ſubmit; and foraſmuch as the Submiſſion treated on, had no relation to my Power given to others by the Believer, from whom Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be expected; but in ſtead thereof to the Power wherewith the Church (as is pretended) is inveſted, we therefore as diſliking the aforeſaid Doctrine, did thus aſſert, <q>This Meaning and Government over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Believers, we take to be contrary to the Principle of Truth, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150237:3"/>Liberty we have in Chriſt Jeſus, for that no <hi>Outward Sentence</hi> or <hi>Matter</hi> whatſoever can obliege the Conſcience, to be approving this or that Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe or Practice, or to be in the Belief of this or that Sentence, Judgment, or Decree, until ſuch time that the Conſcience through the inſhining of Chriſts Light therein, comes to be ſatisfied, and thereby to be bound, and oblieged,</q> ſee <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker, Firſt Part,</hi> pag. 48. and <hi>Third Part,</hi> pag. 53. to 69.128. and therein the Reader will not only find that the <hi>Book of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> given forth by <hi>R. B.</hi> wherein the ſaid Doctrine is held forth, was approved by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> 'Tis certainly known that great Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are frequently uſed to obſtruct the Printing of Friends Papers, unleſs they can ſubmit the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond-day Meeting Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Let but the Deſcription of the ſaid Meeting be conſidered, and that the Office aſſumed by ſuch uncertain unſelected Perſons, is that which renders them Judges in a Spiritual Concern of another mans Conſcience (whether gifted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or no) and I am perſwaded that not one <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of greater Darkneſs, or <hi>more unwarrantable</hi> Preſumption, nor yet that any one Principle with reſpect to Government was ever <hi>read or heard of to be</hi> eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any ſort of People <hi>on the Face of the Earth</hi> with reſpect to ſuch as were accounted Members of their Society, that hath a greater tendency to abridge the Conſcience of her free Exerciſe, or to introduce a more perfect <hi>Map of Confuſion and Anarchy.</hi> See more on this Subject, the <hi>Third Part of the Chriſtian-Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> &amp;c. pag. <hi>29.30.31.32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> at <hi>London</hi> (being a Meeting of uncertain numbers of Perſons, unknown by any Conſtitution of whom to conſiſt, before aſſembled) but alſo a confutation from the Scriptures of Truth of theſe Arguments and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons given for the ſame, further ſhewing that the Scriptures quoted for Proof thereof, are miſapply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and remote from the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But yet notwithſtanding I find in the aforeſaid Treatiſe, Stiled the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> If by the word Rebellion, they mean Rebellion againſt the Dignities, which, in a Tract Entituled</note> 
               <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. That occaſion is taken by the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thereof, to render our Aſſertion,<note>PLACE="marg" <hi>See Pages</hi> 64.65.66.108.109.</note> or the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences deduced by him from it, tending to Confuſion,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>An exalted Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes,</hi> the Authors ſay, I poured out contempt upon, then I conclude the Rebellion is againſt ſixty ſix Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers of a<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Note</hi> The ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is detected in the 2 d. Part of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Quaker,</hi> p. 72. to 92.</note> Paper againſt <hi>John Story</hi> and <hi>John Wilkingſon</hi> in the year <hi>1677.</hi>
               </note> Rebellion, and Ranteriſm, <hi>&amp;c.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150237:3"/>And foraſmuch as it hath been declared that the ſaid Paper was the Act of the</hi> Second-Days Meeting, <hi>as well as of the</hi> Yearly-Meeting, <hi>I may then reaſonably query, Whether the word</hi> Rebellion, <hi>uſed on the aforeſaid Occaſion, may not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as the Symptom of Abominable-Pride, by ſubjecting the Authors thereof to the repute of ſounding a Trumpet to their own imagined Dignity. But ſhould I now make three diſtinct Columes,</hi> viz. <hi>one for the Names of the ſaid ſixty ſix Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers; another for their qualifications and abilities (or rather inabilities, with reſpect to their being</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. p. 116. 117. and conſider well the Contents of the 42 <hi>d.</hi> Diſafection.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of Chriſts</hi> Inward Government;) <hi>and then in the third, ſignifie, theſe are the Dignities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming ſomething tending to Rebellion againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that the Matter of Rebellion, as well as the Rebels are known by this Doctrine,</hi> viz. No outward Sentence can oblige the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in point of faith &amp; duty before conviction by Chriſts Light. <hi>Would they not then appear moſt miſerable Objects of Deriſion and Scorn, eſpecially if in that dreſs preſented to one of their learned</hi> Richard Richardſons <hi>Authors cited in favour of</hi> G. F'<hi>s Errour, namely,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Who can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe think but that <hi>G. F</hi>'s Cauſe is at a low Ebb, ſince he is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to a <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> Works (hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much deſpiſed by him) to bear it up. See <hi>R. R</hi>'s Tract ſtiled <hi>A few Ingredients,</hi> &amp;c. pages 13.18.</note> Richard Baxter <hi>of</hi> Kiderminſter, <hi>great amongſt the</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>whoſe Directory I ſuppoſe, doth not teach any thing ſo contradictory to their fundamental Principles, as the aforeſaid Doctrine rendred tending to Rebellion, is known to be contrary to the antient Doctrine of the People called</hi> Quakers; <hi>for thouſands were convinced of the truth of theſe two plain Sentences, namely,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That every man that cometh into the World was lighted with a meaſure of Chriſts Light in his own Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That 'twas ſafer to have a dependency on this meaſure in our ſelves, than to have an Eye out to the meaſures of others. But if the firſt Publiſher of theſe Doctrines did thus deſign that ſuch as were convinced thereof ſhould at any time after be excomunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if they ſhould not follow ſome Outward Order of his before convinced of its need or ſervice, from the meaſure of Light in themſelves; then it may in truth be ſaid, That a greater cheat never appeared under a religious pretence. But I conclude, that no ſuch deſign was in the beginning, and that when</hi> G. F. <hi>one of the firſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Light in theſe latter days, did begin his Declaration with theſe words.</hi> I am the Light of the World, <hi>his meaning was, that Chriſt was that Light, and not himſelf. To return to my Concern with the</hi> Second-days Meeting <hi>again. But if this diſcourſe ſhould come to the view of the Author of a ſmall Tract ſtiled</hi> Controverſy ended, <hi>'tis to be doubted that the</hi> Second-days Meeting <hi>(though they may account themſelves Dignities) would then be more derided. And why? Becauſe he was rendred a very</hi> Night-bird, <hi>a</hi> Wanderer, <hi>one that looks and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150237:4"/>creeps up and down like a</hi> Vagrant, <hi>as in a ſmall Tract Entituled,</hi> A Winding-Sheet for Controverſy ended, <hi>appears (being alſo reputed to be approved by the</hi> Second-days Meeting; <hi>and the reaſon why he was ſo termed was, becauſe he put not his Name to his Book. Of the like crime the</hi> Second-days Meeting <hi>are now guilty in relation to the Book ſtiled</hi> The Accuſer, <hi>&amp;c. and therefore very unfit to be accounted Dignities, for dignified men are not uſually aſhamed of their Names. Alas! Who ſo blind, as not to know that the Buſineſs of</hi> Church-Government <hi>amongſt one part of the People called</hi> Quakers, <hi>is ſo engroſt between the</hi> Yearly <hi>and</hi> Second-days Meeting, <hi>or amongſt a few of them, as that a Diſlike, whether by particular Churches or Perſons) to either of their Papers, Preſcriptions or Orders, is become matter of ſcandal, if not of Excommunication, and now as worthily reprehended as thoſe aimed at by</hi> W. P. <hi>in his adreſs to</hi> Prot. <hi>pag.</hi> 115. <hi>were by theſe his words.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Alas! who knows not, that loves not to be blind, that the</hi> Church <hi>amongſt them is the</hi> Prieſt-hood, <hi>the few cunning men govern the majority, and entitle their Conceits,</hi> The Canons of Chriſts Church: <hi>and all this comes from the ignorance and idleneſs of the People, that give the Pride and Induſtry of the</hi> Clergy <hi>an opportunity to effect their Crafts upon them, for ſo mean Spirited are the People, as to take all upon truſt for their Souls.</hi>
               </q> At pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent let thus much ſuffice on the occaſion of the <hi>Second-days Meeting</hi> uſing of the word <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas in the <hi>Third Part of the Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> pag. 9. We ſay that there is no ground either from the Scriptures of Truth without us, or Light of Chriſt within us, to believe that any <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſor</hi> can in truth affirm, That there are Outward Preſcriptions and Orders given forth by the Spirit of God, through any one or more mortal men in this our day, which others ought to obey and follow, whether they ſee it their Duty or no; this in the 122. page of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. is termed very frivolous and looſe, and will ſerve only for a pretence to looſe Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who will be apt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they ſee it not their Duty.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs it is cauſe of great amazement, when I do but conſider with what confidence the Pen-man of the Book ſtiled <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. writes touching Rebellion, Confuſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that when all is ſaid relative there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I cannot find the leaſt real ground for uſing thoſe Terms, nor yet any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ground more than ſuch an one, as in the view of a rational man may ſeem to beſpeak the nameleſs Pen-man, and his nameleſs Brethren, dignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves by their own Conſtitution, and being pleaſed with a whimſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal imagination of being (as I take it from their 42 Diſſafection, pages 116. 117. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) viſible Repreſentatives of Chriſts <hi>Inward Government,</hi> are even drunk with deſire after Submiſſion from ſuch as were their Brethren. Alas! What ſort of Dignity can Perſons hiding their Names pretend unto, or how can they expect that any ſhould ſubmit unto their Government. They would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150237:4"/>be reputed to aim only at an Apoſtolick Dignity, but therein the Pen-man hath evidently betrayed their Cauſe. For who ſo ignorant as not to know that the Teſtimony of the <hi>Primitive Quakers</hi> ſeemed the more piercing, when in the Name of the Lord they had declared unto the Sons of Men, that as in the Apoſtles days the Lord was pleaſed to make uſe of mean Perſons, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in Outward Callings to publiſh the Everlaſting Goſpel, ſo is it at this day, but yet I doubt the Pride of the Penman of <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. is now ſo great as to account the Exerciſe of a poor <hi>Shoemaker</hi> therein to be contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, for page 201. he thus ſignifies in his own very words, <hi>By all which he endeavours to make</hi> G. F. <hi>as contemptibbe as he can,</hi> Meaning my declaring in the <hi>Fourth Part of the Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> &amp;c. page 64. that <hi>G. F.</hi> was a poor <hi>Shoemaker,</hi> which <hi>G. F</hi>'s Letter to <hi>John Wilkingſon</hi> did naturally lead me to ſpeak of; but leaſt any ſhould think I was ſo irreligious as to think his Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Trade matter of contempt, I did thereupon thus write. <hi>For his meaunèſs he neither was,</hi>
               <note>PLACE="marg" See 4th. part C. Q. pag. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nor is deſpiſed as we know of, for that cannot ſavour of a Chriſtian Spirit.</hi> And further alſo thus. <hi>I can truly ſay, and ſo I believe many more can,</hi>
               <note>PLACE="marg" See 5th part, p. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that in his Perſon I accounted the Teſtimony of the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the World to confound the wiſe [and God hath choſen the weak things of the World to confound the Mighty, and baſe things of the World, and things which are deſpiſed hath God choſen, yea and things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are not, to bring to nought things which are] that no Fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence. And partly on this ſcore, can I in the Fear of the Lord ſay (and that juſtly too) that he was to me, whil'ſt he kept his Place and Habitation in the Truth) truly honourable.</hi> This clearly ſhews that my Principle and Practice gives no countenance to ſuch a Contempt ſpoken of by the aforeſaid Penman, and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Pride had not led him really to believe that the knowledge of <hi>G. F</hi>'s being a <hi>Shoemaker,</hi> is matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt now, why hath he not taken care to quit himſelf and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from that cenſure, as I have done, but of that I remember not a word in his whole Tract.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known that the Sin uſually beſetting ſome ſort of Governours, is <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Scorn.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſeems to be one part of them complexion of the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pen-man of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. For from his work, he ſeems to me, that he is not only proudly puffed up with the meer empty conceit of <hi>Government,</hi> and with the thoughts of being a <hi>Governour</hi> (whil'ſt in reality oppoſing the exaltation of Chriſts Government in the Heart) but alſo as if he were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext that the Trade of the Perſon whoſe Cauſe he hath eſpouſed ſhould be Recorded, leaſt it ſhould eclipſe the Glory of <hi>G. F.</hi> as no ſuitable Ornament to the Attendance and Outward Enjoyments wherewith he hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted of late years: But this is not all to ſhew the Pride accompanying
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150237:5"/>
               <hi>Truths Oppoſers.</hi> For 'tis known to many that <hi>G. F.</hi> hath been much diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the relation ſignifying that he was a <hi>Shoemaker,</hi> and is that which hath ſeemed to be uppermoſt in his Head, when ſome Friends have had occaſion of diſcourſe with him, which I take to be a meer badge of his <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Scorn.</hi> Who can reaſonably ſuppoſe that <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Adherents did ever make it the ſubject Matter of their Diſcourſes to ſignifie that poor <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> and <hi>Tent-makers</hi> were called to the Work of the Miniſtry, and that in order to the confounding thoſe Learned Rabbies that deſpiſed their mean Education, though now ſuch like are ſearcht into by their Learned <hi>Rich. Richardſon</hi> to ſave the Head of <hi>G. F</hi>'s tottering Cauſe. Alas! 'tis but too plain to me that <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. are better affected with ſuch Grandure as is obtained by the great pretended Succeſſor of <hi>Peter,</hi> than that little worldly Reputation that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his day was accompanied with: and further to clear my Conſcience on this ſubject, let <hi>G. F.</hi> know (whether he can receive it or no) that in probability the Name of a <hi>Quaker</hi> might not have been ſo much deſpiſed by many, as it now is, had he but followed the Example of <hi>W. D.</hi> (one of the firſt Preachers of the Light) and other his Fellow Labourers, keeping, (as they did) at ſome honeſt Outward Calling, inſtead of muddling his head to bring about a Conformity to his <hi>Outward Orders;</hi> for I am fully ſatisfied in my Conſcience that that noyſome ſent which hath ariſen like a ſmoak from the bottomleſs Pit hath been occaſioned from an Antichriſtian Promotion of his <hi>Outward Orders;</hi> and indeed how can it be otherwiſe, ſince he himſelf hath teſtified in a General Epiſtle Printed for <hi>M. W.</hi> in theſe words, <hi>They that do ſo, viz. Set up Outward Things, gathers to themſelves, not unto God:</hi> which is a notable Proof that for many years paſt, he hath been gathering to himſelf, not unto God: and what is the Fruit of ſuch his ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering? To anſwer that queſtion would require a large volumn: I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay it hath ſcattered many of the Flock from the green Paſtures whereon they were feeding, and <hi>Shilohs Streams</hi> wherewith their own Ciſterns were filled, to feed upon the four Leaven of ſome <hi>Hypocritical Phariſees,</hi> &amp; to drink of their muddy waters. If any ſhall think this a digreſſion from the Matter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be treated on, to ſuch I ſay, The ill Savour and groundleſs occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Adverſaries aforeſaid words Confuſion, Rebellion, Looſeneſs, and Ranteriſm, from one whom I took to be in his own ſenſe a Dignity, were the occaſion thereof, and I queſtion not but ſuch as are gifted to diſcern things as they are, will perceive that thoſe words, as applyed by the Pen-man of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> are only to repreſent Men fearing God, and loving Righteouſneſs, in a Bear-Skin, to be worried. 'Tis very apparent that our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhewn their Teeth by their clamorous Treatment, but bleſſed be the Lord, they have no power to Bite: And having rejected many Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are now worthily diſcovered according to their Merit; whereby, if they are rendred a Deriſion to the Heathen, and a Scorn to Fools.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150237:5"/>
            <p>Let them know 'tis but a part of the Reward and Recompenſe of the Fruit of their own doings.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now return to ſpeak more particularly to the matter which from the Title Page may be expected.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third Page</hi> of a ſmall Tract, Stiled, <hi>A Brief Examination and State of Liberty Spiritual,</hi> lately Publiſhed, I find it written in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis a dangerous Principle and pernitious to True Religion, and that which is worſe, 'tis the Root of</hi> Ranteriſme <hi>to aſſert, That nothing is a Duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon thee, but what thou art perſwaded is thy Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine is near of kin to the aforeſaid Doctrine mentioned in the <hi>Accuſer, &amp;c.</hi> and as it relates to Chriſtian Religion, is Repugnant to the Teſtimony of <hi>W. P.</hi> in his <hi>Adreſs</hi> to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> Page 144. in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christian Religion ought to be carried on by that way by which it was Intero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, which was Perſwaſion.</hi> But yet to do the Penman of the Tract Stiled, <hi>A Brief Examination,</hi> &amp;c. Right, He in his following words makes the Application to ſeared, dark and dead Conſciences, as if thereby ſuch were uncondemned; To take his meaning thereon, yet it cannot reaſonably be underſtood otherwiſe than thus, <hi>Viz.</hi> That his aforeſaid Notion muſt have a Tendency that ſome Religious Performance is incumbent on ſuch, though they are not perſwaded thereof. Let us now ſuppoſe that the ſeared dark and dead Conſcience ſhould ſtrictly perform ſome Religious Exerciſe, as his Duty meerly from the direction of another, we are now to enquire, What is the benefit thereof to ſuch? To this let <hi>W. P.</hi> in his aforeſaid <hi>Adr.</hi> to <hi>Prot.</hi> pag. 146. anſwer, his words are theſe, <q>If I believe what ſhe (that is to ſay, the <hi>Church</hi>) believes, only becauſe ſhe believes it, and not becauſe I am convinced in my Underſtanding, and Conſcience of the truth of what ſhe believes, my Faith is falſe though hers be true.</q> And indeed well might <hi>W. P.</hi> ſo teſtifie; for if a blind Offering under the Law was condemnable, it is not juſtifiable under a Goſpel Diſpenſation. Having laid down the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines on which our <hi>Oppoſers</hi> ungodly Conſtructions are founded, I need not enlarge to remove ſuch Conſtructions; let the Reader peruſe what he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready referred unto in the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> and compare the ſame with <hi>W. P.</hi> his <hi>Adreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> pages 77. 91. 92. 93. 94. 95. 140. 141. 144. 146. and divers other Parts, and the Righteouſneſs of what we ſtand for and againſt, will be ſufficiently manifeſted.</p>
            <p>One other Doctrine, pertinent to my purpoſe, occurs in my Memory, it is in the eleventh Page of the aforeſaid Tract ſtiled, <hi>A Brief Examination,</hi> &amp;c. namely, that this is a looſe Plea, <hi>Viz.</hi> 'What haſt thou to do with me, 'leave me to my Freedom, and the Grace of God in my ſelf: which leads me thus to Obſerve.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150237:6"/>
            <p>If our antient Friends <hi>John Story</hi> and <hi>John Wilking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> when articled againſt for not * acting in things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Conſcience,<note>PLACE="marg" Witneſs a part of the <hi>44</hi> Articles exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt them.</note> ſhould have told the buſie Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned therein, <hi>What have you to do with us, leave us to our Freedom, and the Grace of God in our ſelves,</hi> might not this have merited a juſt Approbation from the Primitive Preachers of Chriſts Light in theſe latter days, whoſe Doctrine hath been, <hi>That the Grace is ſufficient, and that every one is to be left to his own meaſure,</hi> antiently underſtood by this manner of ſpeech, <hi>Viz. Our own Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every Reader is now left free to conſider whether a rendering ſuch a Plea of being left to our own Freedom and the Grace of God in our ſelves to be a looſe Plea, is not the mark of one that is departed from the antient Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Truth, a Diſcourager of having a Dependency on the meaſure of Grace in our ſelves; and ſo by natural conſequence may be looked upon as one holding forth a looſe or falſe Liberty, the tendency whereof is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Bleſſed Spirit of Truth, and rebel againſt the perfect Law of Liberty in the Heart.</p>
            <p>It needs no large Coment to ſhew that ſuch, as ſlightly eſteem of a Plea to be left unto our Freedom, and the Grace of God in our ſelves, may eaſily be led like Blind men into any Ditch. It is obſervable that <hi>G. F.</hi> his Party have not only ſlighted ſuch a Plea of being left to the Grace of God in our ſelves, but have a ſort of Veneration for the Outward Directions of another: <hi>C. T.</hi> his Epiſtle, and the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. are to me an evidence of ſuch a Veneration. How much credit this may add to any ſo minded, that have manifeſted a diſlike of the <hi>Preſbyterian Directory,</hi> not altogether for the matter therein contained, but alſo that an outward Directory ſhould be exalted as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Rule under the Miniſtration of Light in this Goſpel Day, let the wiſe in heart judge.</p>
            <p>But to ſtate a caſe in favour of the Doctrine which we oppoſe, let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how it will then look. Suppoſe that the Lord had in every Age under the <hi>Goſpel Diſpenſation,</hi> placed one outward and viſible man to be an eye to ſee for the reſt of the Body, which I dare not grant, and that on that foot <hi>G. F.</hi> ſhould be declared to be that Eye in this our day; yet it would be irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to require ſubmiſſion to his Preſcriptions or Decrees from ſuch as are not convinced that he is placed as ſuch an Eye. If thus much be granted, then the Doctrines already cited, as vindicated by his Party, falls to the ground, becauſe ſuch a grant implyes a convincement, as neceſſary to ſubmiſſion. But if otherwiſe it be affirmed, that he is placed to be an Eye for the Body, and that on that foot his Preſcriptions and Decrees are to be obeyed by Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in Chriſt, whether they are convinced that he is ſuch an Eye, or no, then it opens a Door for many heads, and many horns to ariſe in one day, for that others may pretend to be that Eye as well as he, and may obtain Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150237:6"/>to averre the ſame; and if it ſo happen, that from amongſt Brethren once in Unity, many through the deſire of Vain-Glory ſhould ariſe and claim that Office, the reſt of the Flock might not know unto whoſe Precepts they ought to ſubmit, this is not the only ill Conſequence that might attend, for as on the one hand a Door would be opened for many <hi>Antchriſts</hi> to ariſe undiſcovered, whil'ſt the Grace of God in our ſelves is neglected, (which is no other but that Unction from the Holy One ſpoken of by <hi>John,</hi> as ground of Conſolation to ſuch in whoſe days many <hi>Antichriſts</hi> did ariſe, for that by it all things were known) ſo on the other hand a Door might be opened to many <hi>Hyppocrites</hi> for ſiniſter ends, to entitle themſelves to Memberſhip in ſuch a pretended Church, and to nurture up a Brood of <hi>Shechemites</hi> who rather than run the hazard of that influence which the Frowns of ſome may have on their Trades, or their deſired Marriages, may readily conform to the Dictates of others, though on no better ground than the<note>PLACE="marg" <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.24.</note> 
               <hi>Shechemites</hi> did, when at the Requeſt of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Sons, and Perſwaſion of <hi>Hamor</hi> they were Circumciſed, not only to obtain <hi>Dinah</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but other ſeeming Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in their Eye. As a Warning to all, I cannot but ſay, beware of the Snare and Gin that accompanies the eſpouſing of ſuch beloved Intereſts with no leſs than the making Shipwrack of a good Conſcience towards Good, leaſt that which was thirſted after, as ſweet and pleaſant, do not only become bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto you, but alſo leaſt the Indignation of the Lord ſhould break forth, and you come to ſuffer a <hi>Spiritual Death</hi> as to your Inward States and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards God, even as he ſuffered <hi>Jacobs Sons</hi> to ſlay the <hi>Shechemites</hi> with the Edge of the Sword, after they were Circumciſed for ſiniſter Ends.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe I have of the Snare attending many through Conformity to other mens Lines, made ready to their hand in a blind obedience, occaſions me to bleſs the Lord, that there are yet a Remnant who can rejo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Remembrance of this joyful ſound, TO YOUR OWN, TO YOUR OWN: meaning <hi>The Meaſure of Gods Gift and Grace in our ſelves.</hi> The embracing that Exhortation became an Ancert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> many a weatied Soul, who were hurryed from Mountain to Hill, ſeeking Reſt, but finding none. Oh! that the skirts of the Deceiver of Nations under theſe ruſty Doctrines (now furbiſht up in our day) may be more and more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, that ſo no Allegiance thereto may be entayled to our Poſterities, leaſt ſome proud <hi>Phariſee</hi> deſpiſing, as well as neglecting his lawful outward Calling, make his Fingers heavier than the Loins of the decryed Prelates. And if this ſmall Tract, as well as other Diſcoveries of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> become as ſo many Darts to pierce the Bowels of that Cauſe eſpouſed by thoſe nameleſs Perſons, terming themſelves <hi>The Second-days Meeting,</hi> ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n as an arrow ſhot at an Adventure pierced <hi>Ahab</hi> between the joynts of his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150237:7"/>when diſguiſed to ſave hiſelf, then let us ſay, <hi>Bleſſed be the God of our Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To return again, I ſhall further demonſtrate the inconſiſtency of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Doctrines with what <hi>W. P.</hi> in his <hi>Adreſs to Proteſtants</hi> teacheth in pag. 139.140. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <q>That we ſhould have external Guardians of our Faith and Religion upon us, after we are come to years of diſcretion, is not to obtain greater Freedom, it is a knowing and reaſonable, and not blind Obedience that commends a man. Children ſhould be ruſed, becauſe they have no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or choice, but becauſe it is not ſo with Men, Reaſon ought to conduct them in their Duty, that the Service they perform to God may be ſuch as the Apoſtle calls <hi>a reaſonable one.</hi> The Noble <hi>Bereans</hi> — ſuch as would ſee with their own Eyes, and that dare not to transfer the right of Examination to any mortal Man.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis now with me to treat of ſome things which I take to be the fruit of the aforeſaid Doctrines eſpouſed by ſuch as are reputed to be of <hi>G. F.</hi>'s Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Blaykling</hi> made a challenge in writing on this wiſe; <hi>Let that man come forth in the whole Nation that can juſtly charge him</hi> (meaning <hi>G. F.</hi>) <hi>with ſuch a Spirit from his Childhood,</hi> meaning, as his foregoing words did ſhew, <hi>a careleſs, looſe, libertine or dark Spirit,</hi> which I ſignified to <hi>G. F.</hi> with this Anſwer; <hi>If thou wilt acknowledge that the publication of Lies, the making uſe of a Certificate in thy favour given forth by a man that thou thy ſelf knows, knew nothing of ſome of the Matters whereof by the words of his Teſtimony he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to clear thee, giving Inſtructions to others to perform Duty, and yet take Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to violate the ſame thy ſelf, as if thou wouldſt have Friends to follow thy words, but not thy Example, be the fruit of a careleſs, looſe, libertine, or dark Spirit, then I am the man in this Nation who am ready to come forth to charge thee with the fruit of a careleſs, looſe, libertine, dark Spirit, and to juſtifie the charge againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding ſuch my Anſwer, and my frequent Endeavours largely ſignified of in the <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker in Five Parts,</hi> to this effect; <hi>That</hi> G. F. <hi>might condeſcend to a hearing before Friends of what I had to lay to his Charge,</hi> yet he hath not ſo condeſcended, but is kept like a guilty Perſon behind the Curtain. In order to a diſcovery of part of his Errours, ſee his Name is the Index to the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker in Five Parts,</hi> taking eſpecial notice of that looſe, if not ranting Spirit accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying <hi>John Blaykling,</hi> when he aſcribed that honour and Work to <hi>G. F.</hi> which we acknowledge to be due to, and proceed from, none but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; his words are theſe; <hi>Whoſe Eternal Honour and Bleſſed Renown ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, yea his preſence, and the dropping of his tender words in the Lords Love, was my Souls nouriſhment.</hi> We know Eternal Honour is due to none but God himſelf, according to the frequent concluſion of Friends in Prayer to God;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150237:7"/>(namely, <hi>To thee alone be Eternal Honour and Renown for evermore</hi>) and therefore it may well be queried, whether ſuch Language hath no a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch ſort of <hi>Ranteriſm,</hi> that hath termed a mortal man to be God: and if to put no diſtinction between good, and ſome things that are evil, be alſo the fruit of a ranting Spirit, I doubt not but that <hi>G. F.</hi> and many of his Party are in a high degree guilty thereof, with reſpect to their conceptions of him, as well as his own conceptions of himſelf; for I doubt not but that he and others on his behalf are ſo puft up with vain Imagination, or that which is worſe, as that they conclude that for many years paſt, if not from his Childhood, <hi>he neither hath nor can err;</hi> and on that foot, let his tongue run ever ſo extravagantly evil, I am perfwaded that neither he, nor many of his Adherents do put any difference between that and the thing that is good. See the <hi>Fourth, Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Seventh Parts</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> for further ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Principles and practiſes whereof <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Party are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to the diſhonour of God, his Truth, and People, and when compared with all that is ſaid againſt any of the ſaid Parts, then conſider whether ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things therein contained, and not denyed by <hi>G. F.</hi> or his Party, do not worthily merit the cenſure of a grand deviation from the anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt profeſſed Principle and Practiſe of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſo far as they have a tendency ſlightly to eſteem of leaving Friends to the Grace of God in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (and inſtead thereof, to introduce a Submiſſion to ſome proud Perſons endeavouring to dignifie themſelves by a zealous promoting of <hi>G. F.</hi>'s Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders amongſt ſuch as are diſſatisfie therewith) whether they may not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be termed the very marks and tokens of ſuch a looſe libertine Spirit, <hi>That by the meaſure of Gods Grace in the Children of Light, is, and for ever will be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very mentioning a zealous promotion of <hi>G. F.</hi>'s Orders brings to my remembrance, that <hi>W. P.</hi> in his <hi>Adr. to Prot.</hi> pag. 91. tells us, <hi>That it</hi> (meaning the Scriptures) <hi>concerns the whole Life and Converſation of a man, but every Paſſage in it, is not therefore fit to be ſuch an Article of Faith as upon which</hi> Chriſtian Communion <hi>ought, or ought not to be maintained.</hi> This leads me thus to query.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether then ſuch amongſt <hi>G. F</hi>'s Party as declare diſunion with another Perſon, on the meer foot of that other Perſons conſcientious refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal to propoſe the Intentions of his Marriage to a Meeting-of Women di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from Men, be not a Badge of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> eſpecially when the leaſt Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of ſuch a Proceeding is not to be found in the <hi>Seriptures of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether the declaration of diſunion on no other ground, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the laſt cited words of <hi>W. P.</hi> carries not with it this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150237:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Though</hi> Chriſtian-Communion <hi>may be maintained without making every Paſſage in Scripture an</hi> Article of Faith, <hi>as eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to ſuch</hi> Communion, <hi>yet not one</hi> Jota <hi>of an Order ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by</hi> G. F<hi>'s Party, can be diſpenſed with to maintain the antient Fellowſhip of the People called</hi> Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether this be not to put a greater eſteem on ſuch an Order, than the very Scriptures of Truth themſelves, let the ingenious Reader judge.</p>
            <p>What Credit can our Oppoſers think will ever accrew to their Cauſe, whileſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Adr. to Prot.</hi> ſhall paſs for ſound and Chriſtian Doctrine. Our Adverſaries muſt needs be reduced to this Dilemma, either to condemn the Chriſtian Diſcourſes contained therein, and ſo in oppoſition thereto hold up their Enſign of <hi>Church-Authority</hi> and <hi>Impoſition,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt,</hi> by which the antient Principle and Practice of the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> will be condemned, or elſe to ſtand by the ſame; and then their late flight of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the Grace of God in our ſelves, and approving the Doctrine of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Church, whether Believers ſee it their Duty or no, muſt be repudiated, as that which can nouriſh no better Devotion than that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Blindneſs</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the <hi>Mother.</hi> And though the nameleſs Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. hath endeavoured to render himſelf and Brethren as acquitted of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovation,</hi> yet he hath been as ſucceſsleſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as if he had undertaken to ſodder <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay</hi> together. And why? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath become an <hi>Advocate</hi> for men who have departed from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Paths (as is largely manifeſted in the firſt ſeven Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi>) the Footſteps of pureſt Antiquity and beſt Examples, which is ſuch a ſort of Preſumption, as that <hi>W. P. Adr. to Prot.</hi> pag. 92. tells us; <hi>That it was juſt with God, that Error and Confuſion ſhould be the Conſequences of thoſe Adventures, nor has it ever failed to follow them.</hi> Our Oppoſers may come in as Living Witneſſes to the truth of ſuch his Teſtimony, or their work is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted (in the ſeven Parts of the <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker</hi>) <hi>To be the very Map of Confuſion and Errour;</hi> ſhewing no more Charity (ſo far as I can perceive) for ſome ſuch as were their Brethren (now diſſenting from them) than Biſhop <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nner</hi> did, for ſuch as anſwered not to his ſatisfaction this Queſtion. <hi>What ſay you to the Sacrament of the</hi> Altar? Bleſſed be the Lord that our Oppoſers have not ſo much Power as he had; How remote the uncharitable Conſtructions of ſuch as were our Brethren, are from the Diſcourſe mentioned in 92 pag. of the <hi>Adr. to Prot.</hi> he that runs may read. The words are theſe. <hi>What man loves God and Chriſt, ſeeks Peace and Concord, that would not rejoyce if all our Animoſities and Vexations about Matters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150237:8"/>of Religion were buryed in this one Confeſſion of Jeſus, the great Author and Lord of the</hi> Chriſtian-Religion, <hi>ſo often loſt in pretending to conteſt for it.</hi> And pag. 95. is cited by way of Approbation the words of that great man <hi>J. Hales,</hi> VIZ. <hi>That it is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, and not the Identi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (or oneneſs) of conceit, which the Holy Ghoſt requires at the hands of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Much more might be cited out of the ſaid <hi>Adr. to Prot.</hi> in our favour, with reſpect to what we ſtand for and againſt, but at preſent let this ſuffice as a proper Umpirage in the caſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now conclude with what doth freſhly occur in my memory, as the ſum and ſubſtance of many ſweet and heavenly Declarations in the Name of the Lord by our antient Brethren, on this wiſe; <hi>Draw water out of your own Wells, let it be your own, and not anothers. Look not unto us, but unto the Lord. We can be taken from you; but your Teacher can never be removed into a Corner. We preach not our ſelves, but Chriſt in you. We are but Ambaſſadors in his Name to turn you from Darkneſs to Light, from the power of Satan unto God, that ſo by the meaſure of the Light of Chriſt in your ſelves, you might be eſtabliſh in the Truth which changeth not. It is the Gift of the Fathers Love that we come to exalt over all, Chriſt in</hi> Male <hi>and</hi> Female <hi>the Hope of Glory. Our Labour is, that you who were not natural Branches, may come to be engrafted into Chriſt the Vine, and then to live under your own Vine; that ſo if in your day the Voice of a Stranger ſhould be ſounded in your Ears, ſaying,</hi> Lo here is Chriſt, <hi>or</hi> There is Chriſt; <hi>you might no more go forth, but ſtay at home, as thoſe who are ingaged in a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Warfare, having this incouragement from the</hi> Pſalmiſt, She that ſtays at home divides the Spoil.</p>
            <p>This was the ſound of the Antients of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Spirit, when the Word of the Lord through them was piercing like a Dart to the Liver, terrible to the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> but yet as a lovely Song to thoſe whoſe Faces were <hi>Sion</hi> ward; and the ſame Spirit that led them to treat as aforeſaid, did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently move on their Spirits, to enform us of thoſe Rocks whereon the Sons of Men have been enclined to ſplit, and thoſe By-paths wherein the wayfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man hath been apt to err, on this wiſe. <hi>In Ages paſt the Sons of Men have been inclined to ſet up, or be in the Obſervation of ſome Outward thing, and to have their Eye thereto more than unto the Word nigh in the Heart.</hi> This was <hi>Iſrael</hi> Sin before then appearance of Chriſt in the Fleſh, when they made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves a <hi>Golden Calf</hi> ſaying, <hi>Theſe are thy Gods, Oh</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. This was the Sin reproved by <hi>Paul</hi> on this wiſe, <hi>But now ſeeing ye know God, yea, rather are known by him; How turn ye again unto the weak and beggerly Elements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was and is the miſtake in moſt Societies and Churches profeſſing Chriſtianity in Modern Times, whereon I need not dilate.</p>
            <p>The Teſtimony of our antient Friends, by Declarations, Diſputes and Printing, are yet as living Evidences in many Breaſts; the Remembrance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150237:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereof ſeems to be cauſe of Aſtoniſhment, That any of the antient Flock ſhould give occaſion to <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> or <hi>the Church of God</hi> to Impeach them of falling into the like Snare. But that which ſeems to render the matter yet worſe is this; That they ſhould ſpeak well of thoſe Antient Labourers (<hi>whoſe Doctrines,</hi> as aforeſaid, <hi>dropt as the Dew</hi>) whilſt Perſecuting others abiding therein; much like unto thoſe <hi>Who Garniſhed the Sepulchers of the Prophets that Propheſied of Chriſt,</hi> but when He came, were found <hi>Perſecutors of Him and his Followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Eſtabliſh his People on CHRIST JESUS, The ROCK OF AGES, and turn the Hearts of our <hi>Perſecuting Oppoſers,</hi> that in a ſenſe of their <hi>Backſliding</hi> and <hi>Errours, They may confeſs unto God,</hi> and through True Repentance be <hi>made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his Mercy,</hi> and then, no doubt but the <hi>Antient Love</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> in the <hi>Truth,</hi> will be again Renewed, to the Conſolation of one anothers Soules in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> ſaith my Soul. <hi>William Rogers.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
